{
  "title": "General_Aptitude-_CSE - General_Aptitude-_CSE — Slot 2 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "General_Aptitude-_CSE — Slot 2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>According to the map shown in the figure, which one of the following statements is correct?  <br>\nNote: The figure shown is representative. <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\General_Aptitude-_CSE\\q60_d7b5bf82.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The library is located to the northwest of the canteen.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The hospital is located to the east of the chemistry lab.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The chemistry lab is to the southeast of the physics lab.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The classrooms and canteen are next to each other.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The chemistry lab is to the southeast of the physics lab.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460096/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider the relationships among P, Q, R, S, and T:  <br><br>\nP is the brother of Q.<br>\nS is the daughter of Q.<br>\nT is the sister of S. <br>\nR is the mother of Q.\n<br><br>\nThe following statements are made based on the relationships given above.<br><br>\nR is the grandmother of S.<br>\nP is the uncle of S and T.<br>\nR has only one son.<br>\nQ has only one daughter.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following options is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (1) and (2) are true.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Both (1) and (3) are true.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only (3) is true.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only (4) is true.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (1) and (2) are true.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460097/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The average marks obtained by a class in an examination were calculated as 30.8. However, while checking the marks entered, the teacher found that the marks of one student were entered incorrectly as 24 instead of 42. After correcting the marks, the average becomes 31.4. How many students does the class have? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>25</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>28</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>30</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>32</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>30</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460098/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-3#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The CEO's decision to downsize the workforce was considered myopic because it sacrificed long-term stability to accommodate short-term gains.  <br>\nSelect the most appropriate option that can replace the word \"myopic\" without changing the meaning of the sentence. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>visionary</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>shortsighted</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>progressive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>innovative</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>shortsighted</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460099/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Ravi had _____________ younger brother who taught at _____________ university. He was widely regarded as _____________ honorable man.  <br>\nSelect the option with the correct sequence of articles to fill in the blanks. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a; a; an</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>the; an; a</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a; an; a</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>an; an; a</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>a; a; an</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460100/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>In the 4 x 4 array shown below, each cell of the first three rows has either a\ncross (X) or a number.<br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\General_Aptitude-_CSE\\q65_f95e0861.webp\"><br>\nThe number in a cell represents the count of the immediate neighboring cells\n(left, right, top, bottom, diagonals) NOT having a cross (X). Given that the last row\nhas no crosses (X), the sum of the four numbers to be filled in the last row is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>11</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>12</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>9</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>11</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422897/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A cube is to be cut into 8 pieces of equal size and shape. Here, each cut should be\nstraight and it should not stop till it reaches the other end of the cube.<br>\nThe minimum number of such cuts required is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>8</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422898/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>The pie charts depict the shares of various power generation technologies in the\ntotal electricity generation of a country for the years 2007 and 2023.<br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\General_Aptitude-_CSE\\q63_e902d47d.webp\"><br>\nThe renewable sources of electricity generation consist of Hydro, Solar and Wind.\nAssuming that the total electricity generated remains the same from 2007 to 2023,\nwhat is the percentage increase in the share of the renewable sources of electricity\ngeneration over this period? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>25%</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>50%</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>77.50%</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>62.50%</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>62.50%</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422899/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>A person sold two different items at the same price. He made 10% profit in one\nitem, and 10% loss in the other item. In selling these two items, the person made a\ntotal of <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1% profit</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2% profit</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1% loss</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2% loss</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>1% loss</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422900/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Sequence the following sentences in a coherent passage.<br><br>\nP:    This fortuitous geological event generated a colossal amount of energy and heat that resulted in the rocks rising to an average height of 4 km across the contact zone.\n<br>Q:    Thus, the geophysicists tend to think of the Himalayas as an active geological event rather than as a static geological feature.\n<br>R:    The natural  process  of  the  cooling  of  this massive  edifice  absorbed  large quantities of atmospheric carbon dioxide, altering the earth?s atmosphere and making it better suited for life.\n<br>S:    Many millennia ago, a breakaway chunk of bedrock from the Antarctic Plate collided with the massive Eurasian Plate. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>QPSR</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>QSPR</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>SPRQ</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>SRPQ</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>SPRQ</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422901/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>In the sequence 6, 9, 14, x, 30, 41, a possible value of x is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>25</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>21</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>18</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>20</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>21</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422902/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>For positive non-zero real variables \\(x \\) and  \\(y \\), if\n<br><br> \\(\n\\ln \\left(\\frac{x+y}{2}\\right)=\\frac{1}{2}[\\ln (x)+\\ln (y)]\n\\) <br><br>\nthen, the value of  \\(\\frac{x}{y}+\\frac{y}{x} \\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1/2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422903/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>In an engineering college of 10,000 students, 1,500 like neither their core branches\nnor other branches. The number of students who like their core branches is 1/4th of\nthe number of students who like other branches. The number of students who like\nboth their core and other branches is 500.<br>\nThe number of students who like their core branches is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1,800</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3,500</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1,600</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1,500</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>1,800</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422904/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-3#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Two wizards try to create a spell using all the four elements, water, air, fire, and earth. For this, they decide to mix all these elements in all possible orders. They also  decide  to  work  independently.  After  trying  all  possible  combination  of elements, they conclude that the spell does not work.<br>\nHow  many  attempts  does  each  wizard  make  before  coming  to  this  conclusion, independently? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>24</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>48</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>16</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>12</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>24</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422905/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>If '\\( \\rightarrow \\)' denotes increasing order of intensity, then the meaning of the words\n[walk \\( \\rightarrow \\) jog \\( \\rightarrow \\) sprint] is analogous to [bothered \\( \\rightarrow \\) ________ \\( \\rightarrow \\) daunted].<br>\nWhich one of the given options is appropriate to fill the blank? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>phased</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>phrased</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>fazed</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>fused</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>fazed</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422906/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}